Finding aid for the Karl G. Yoneda papers, 1892-1998, bulk 1925-1989 LSC.1592
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 1. Communist and Labor Union Activities, 1909-1993
  - 1.6. Alaskan Cannery Workers Union, 1930-1942, 1947-1989
    - Bulletins, Leaflets, and Pamphlet Issued by the Alaska Cannery Workers Union, Local 20195, A.F. of L., San Francisco, California, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      ????·?????????????? Arasuka Kyanari Rodosha Kumiai Buruten = Alaska Cannery Workers Union. No. 1 (Jan., 1937)-no. 2 (Feb./Mar., 1937), Sept. 1937, no. 2 (Feb., 1938)-no. 3 (Mar., 1938), Apr. 5, 1938, Apr. 20, 1938, and Apr. 28, 1938; one leaflet published in 1938; and a pamphlet: Yoneda, Karl G. ????·??????????? Sen-kyuhyaku-sanjuroku, sanjushichi-nen no Taiheiyo Kaiun Higyo = The Pacific Coast Maritime Strike of 1936, '37. San Francisco: Alaska Cannery Workers Union A.F. of L. Local 20195, 1937.
    - Miscellaneous Materials Regarding the Alaska Cannery Workers' Union, 1934-1942 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Includes one document listing "opening prices of canned salmon" in 1937; seventeen leaves of documents on Alaska Packers Association; Resolution #1 for Alaska Cannery Workers' Union; the Union's rules and order; nineteen leaves of the court hearing on Cannery Workers' and Farm Labors' Union Local no. 18257 vs. the American Federation of Labor in the Superior Court, King county, the State of Washington; photographs; a meeting announcement; news clippings; and photocopies of letters and membership books, etc.
    - News Clippings, 1936-1938, 1947-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Materials Related to ILWU Local 37 Alaska Cannery Workers, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1.7. International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU), 1946-1992
    Contains materials regarding Yoneda's ILWU activities. Includes arbitration documents regarding Yoneda's re-registration as a longshoreman after his incarceration to the Manzanar War Relocation Center and enlistment of the U.S. military service during World War II; and meeting minutes, reports, a photograph, transcripts of his speech, resolutions, bulletins, fliers, news clippings, and other miscellaneous materials related to ILWU.
    - Arbitration Regarding Yoneda's Re-registration as a Longshoreman, 1946-1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Documents regarding Yoneda's appeal for re-registration as a longshoreman after his incarceration to the Manzanar War Relocation Center and enrollment in the U.S. Military Service during World War II along with subsequent documents of his injuries and retirement. Includes Yoneda's application letters listing Yoneda's earnings as a longshoreman from 1936 to 1942, with evidential documents, including his workbooks and receipts for the International Longshoremen's Association during 1936 to 1938; correspondence between Yoneda and the Union Local 10; arbitration documents for Yoneda's re-granting his status issued on February 14, 1946; his application forms; news clippings; and photocopies of Yoneda's registration for ILWU and membership card and workbook.
    - ILWU Conventions, 1973-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Materials regarding ILWU conventions, including transcripts of Yoneda's speech, meeting minutes, resolutions, a photograph of Yoneda attending the 24th convention, and news clippings.
    - Pacific Coast Pensioners Association, 1974, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Minutes and news clippings for the seventh Annual Convention held in September 1974 and bulletins.
    - Warehouse Union Local 6 for the Duty Free Shoppers Employees, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Local 6 bulletins, letters, fliers, Yoneda's drafts of the fliers for the employees of the Duty Free Shoppers, news clippings, a pamphlet for the ILWU, and other documents.
    - Miscellaneous Materials Regarding the ILWU, 1956-1992 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1.8. American Communist Party, 1968-1993
    Contains minutes, reports, conference materials, transcripts of Yoneda's talk, and resolutions of the Communist Party of America, Northern California district Asian Pacific Islander Commission meetings and conferences from 1968 to 1993. Also includes correspondence, news clippings, negatives, and other miscellaneous materials related to the Communist Party of America.
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1971-1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1976-1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Northern California District Asian Pacific Islander Commission Meetings and Conferences, 1988-1991 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Materials Regarding the American Communist Party, 1968-1993 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- 2. World War II Internment, 1941 December 8-1994
  Series comprised of materials regarding the Japanese American World War II internment experience. Materials written by Yoneda include postal telegrams, correspondence, leaflets, reports, meeting minutes, and evacuation claim forms. There are folders containing materials created or circulated in the Manzanar War Relocation Center during Yoneda's incarceration; and folders containing materials collected after the war. Includes correspondence, photographs, pamphlets, brochures, fliers, and news clippings.
  - 2.1 Manzanar War Relocation Center, 1941 December 8-1945 August 15
    Comprised of materials regarding the Manzanar War Relocation Center. Contains materials collected from immediately after the Attack on Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941 through the end of the war. There are materials collected in the Manzanar War Relocation Center during Yoneda's incarceration, including announcements for internees, a blue print of the camp, block managers' reports and meeting minutes, a draft of the constitution of the camp, instruction to evacuees volunteering for employment outside, and petition to the president for U.S. military enlistment. In the camp, Yoneda served as a block leader as well as a member of the Manzanar Citizens Federation. Materials regarding the Manzanar Citizens Federation, including its rules and regulations, and transcripts of Yoneda's speech delivered at the meeting, are included. There are reports and letters written by Yoneda and/or Tom Yamazaki and Koji Ariyoshi, documenting activities and conditions of the camp. There is also a report by the War Relocation Authority, "Background for the Relocation Program," describing the evacuees and justifying the relocation program. The materials include postal telegrams, correspondence, leaflets, meeting minutes, a blue print, photographs, pamphlets, brochures, and news clippings.
    - Documents Collected before Evacuation, 1941 December 8-1942 March 21 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Documents collected starting from immediately after the Attack on Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941 through March 21, 1942, two days before Yoneda voluntarily evacuated to the assembly center at the Manzanar War Relocation Center. Contains materials written by Yoneda, including postal telegrams, correspondence, leaflets, and meeting minutes. Also includes materials issued by the government offices and news clippings, depicting Anti-Japanese sentiment in the United States.
    - Camp Records (1 of 6), 1942 March 23-April 30 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Documents collected during Yoneda's incarceration in the Manzanar War Relocation Center, from March 23, 1942 through April 30, 1942.
    - Camp Records (2 of 6), 1942 May 1-31 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Documents collected during Yoneda's incarceration in the Manzanar War Relocation Center, May 1-31, 1942.
    - Camp Records (3 of 6), 1942 June 1-30 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Documents collected during Yoneda's incarceration in the Manzanar Relocation Center, June 1-June 30, 1942.
    - Camp Records (4 of 6), 1942 July 1-31 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Documents collected during Yoneda's incarceration in the Manzanar War Relocation Center, July 1-31, 1942.
    - Camp Records (5 of 6), 1942 August 1-October 6 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Documents collected during Yoneda's incarceration in the Manzanar War Relocation Center, August 1-October 6, 1942.
    - Camp Records (6 of 6), 1942 October-December 31 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Documents collected after Yoneda left the Manzanar War Relocation Center. Mainly includes publications, such as "A Chronology of Evacuation and Relocation from Dec. 7, 1941 through Oct. 30, 1942," and news clippings. There are extracts from Japanese journals published in 1942, including articles about the internment camps written by Japanese citizens who were deported from the United States after evacuation.
    - Materials Regarding the World War II Internment Collected between 1943 and 1944, 1943-1944, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Includes a bibliography, "Evacuation!: A Selected Bibliography on the Japanese Evacuation," by Northern California Office Fellowship of Reconciliation; letters; pamphlets, 'segregation of Loyal and Disloyal Japanese in Relocation Centers, Message from the President of the United States, Transmitting Report on Senate Resolution no. 166 Relating to Segregation of Loyal and Disloyal Japanese in Relocation Centers and Plans for Future Operation of Such Centers' and "The Displaced Japanese-Americans" by American Council on Public Affairs.
    - Photographs, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Yoneda and his family photographs during their incarceration in the Manzanar War Relocation Center in 1942. Depicting their life in the camp, there are photographs of their barracks with other internees, Taeko and Koji Ariyoshi's wedding, and other internees' funerals. Includes negatives, slides, and some reproduction.
    - News Clippings (1 of 3), 1941 February 7, 1941 December 8-1942 December 10 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - News Clippings (2 of 3), 1943 January 29-1945 August 15 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - News Clippings (3 of 3), 1943 February 18-August 16 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      One unbound scrapbook.
    - Jap Hunting Licenses, 1941 December 15 (Box 48, Folder 2)
      The sign, "Jap hunting licenses, issued here, open season--now no limit," and the license issued pasted on a paperboard (44 x 35 cm.).
    - "Gripping Scenes Mark Departure of Jap Auto Caravan", 1942 March 23 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      A news clipping from "Los Angeles Evening and Express" on March 23, 1942, "Gripping Scenes Mark Departure of Jap Auto Caravan." The article is pasted on a paperboard (44 x 35 cm.)
  - 2.2 Postwar Materials Relating to the World War II Internment, 1945-1990
    Contains correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and pamphlets collected after World War II. Materials are arranged by subjects or events related to the Japanese American internment, and listed on the basis of greater value of the materials.
    - Evacuation Claim, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Yoneda's evacuation claim forms under the Evacuation Claim Act of July 2, 1948, itemizing loss suffered as a result of evacuation from a military area during the war.
    - Black Dragon Society, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Materials regarding ??? Kokuryukai = Black Dragon Society, which consists of pro-Japan militarists, who are mostly Kibei Nisei (=Japanese American second generation but grown up in Japan). Includes photographs of inscription etched on the ridge at the Manzanar reservoir in 1943, a leaflet, a letter from George Thow, a hand drawn map, and news clippings. Photographs and the leaflet are annotated in English by Yoneda. Negatives are also included.
    - Manzanar Riot, Joe Kurihara, and Harry Ueno, 1967-1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Includes photocopies of documents by the U.S. Naval Intelligence Service on the disloyal elements in the Manzanar, collection of news clippings of "Point of No Return" by Tad Ueno published in Rafu Shimpo along with Yoneda's comments, other review articles, notes of interview with Satoru Kamikawa, letters, photocopies of interview transcripts of Harry Y. Ueno and Togo Tanaka, conducted by the California State University, Fullerton Oral History Program Japanese American Oral History Project.
    - Earl Warren Controversy over the Japanese American Evacuation, 1958-1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Contains mainly news clippings about Earl Warren's controversy over the Japanese American evacuation.
    - Farewell to Manzanar, 1973, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Reviews and comments on a film, "Farewell to Manzanar." Also includes correspondence among Yoneda and James D. Houston and Jeanne Wakatsuki Houston.
    - Japanese Americans: The Untold Story, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Reviews and comments on a book, "Japanese Americans: The Untold Story." Includes Yoneda's comments and a booklet, "Critical Reviews of Japanese Americans: The Untold Story" edited and published by Ethnic Studies Committee, Asian- American Student Alliance, Stanford University, in 1971.
    - Reviews on Publications about the World War II Internment, 1949-1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      News clippings including reviews on publications about the World War II Internment.
    - Executive Order 9066 Exhibition, 1971-1976, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs, letters, news clippings, and brochures.
    - News Clippings on the World War II Internment, 1945-1962 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - News Clippings on the World War II Internment, 1973-1988 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Materials, 1946-1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Includes letters, brochures, maps, and fliers. There is an office memorandum from the United States government regarding the detention of Communists in the event of sudden difficulty with Russia in photocopied format.
  - 2.3 Pilgrimages and Reunions, 1954, 1969-1994
    Materials regarding the Manzanar pilgrimage, Manzanar reunion, Tule Lake pilgrimage, and pilgrimages of other Japanese American concentration camps, including Topaz, Poston, Heart Mountain, Amache, Minedoka, Rohwer, Walerga Assembly Center, and Payallup camps. Contains transcripts of Yoneda's speeches, poems, and a tribute delivered at the Manzanar pilgrimages, photographs, correspondence, programs, lyrics of songs, pamphlets, articles, and documents regarding the Manzanar State project by State of California Department of Parks and Recreation. There are materials issued by the Manzanar Committee, including correspondence, statements, booklets, and pamphlets.
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1954, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Includes drafts of Yoneda's speech and poem titled as "Manzanar After 40 Years."
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Includes Yoneda's speech and poem titled as "Manzanar: For Peace."
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      20th Annual Manzanar Pilgrimage: Dedicated to the Memory of Elaine Black Yoneda. There are two copies of drafts compiled by Yoneda, "A Few Reminders of Manzanar: 1942-1989," and Yoneda's transcripts of "Tribute to Elaine."
    - Manzanar Pilgrimage, 1990-1994 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Manzanar Reunion, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Tule Lake Pilgrimage, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Tule Lake Pilgrimage, 1975-1982, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Topaz, Poston, Heart Mountain, Amache, Minedoka, Rohwer, Walerga Assembly Center, Payallup Camps Pilgrimages, 1975-1981 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- 3. Military Services of Japanese Americans, 1940-1995, bulk 1944-1950
  Series contains materials regarding Japanese American military servivces during World War II. Includes propaganda materials, campaign maps, interrogation reports of the Japanese prisoners of war, correspondence, documents circulated in the Manzanar War Relocation Center, photographs, documents for the Veterans Affairs, publications by the U.S. military organizations, pamphlets, brochures, news clippings, and others.
  - 3.1 Office of the War Information Psychological Warfare Team, the China- Burma-India Office, 1940-1995, bulk 1944-1950
    Comprised mainly of propaganda materials issued by the Office of the War Information (OWI) Psychological Warfare Team, the China-Burma-India Office, including ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets], newspapers, pamphlets, and a military song book produced between 1944 and 1945. There are maps of Asia, Burma, and China, with handwritten notes of the US Office of the War Information's campaign and battle planning in English and Japanese. Also includes interrogation reports of Japanese prisoners of war conducted by Yoneda and photographs depicting the USOWI activities in Burma, India, and China during the battles. There are two postcards with drawings by Keiko Akiba (= Keiko Fukuda), which were sent to her father who was a Japanese soldier killed during the Burma Campaign. Materials collected after the war include issues of "Ex-CBI Roundup: China, Burma, India" and materials regarding Veterans Affairs.
    - Propaganda Materials (1 of 6), 1944 April 16 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      One scrapbook titled: USOWI CBI Powai, Assam, India: Book A, with a label, "Psychological Warfare Team U.S.O.W.I. A.P.O. 689 I.B.T Book no. 16 issued to T/3 Karl Yoneda." Dated on April 16, 1944. Contains propaganda materials, such as ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets], pamphlets, maps, and newspapers (?? Jisei; ?????? Senjin Nyusu; ????? Biruma Shinbun; ?????? Minai Taiheiyo Shuho; ?? Meisei; ???? Gunjin Shinbun; and ?? Shinsei), match cases, pins, letters, and postcards, in Japanese, English, Chinese, and Burmese. English translation, synopsis, and explanatory paragraphs are attached to most of the materials. The propaganda materials were prepared by Ledo, India, U.S. Office of War Information (OWI), New Delhi, India Office of Strategic Services (OSS), Chungking, China, Political Military Committee of National Government of China (PMNC), and New Delhi, India, South East Asian Command-British Psychological Warfare Division (SEAC-BPWD). Also includes a content list in English compiled by Yoneda.
    - Propaganda Materials (2 of 6), 1944-1945 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      One scrapbook titled: Book B, with a label, "Psychological Warfare branch U.S.O.W.I. A.P.O. 627 C.T. Kunming, China issued to Karl Yoneda." Contains propaganda materials, such as ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets], pamphlets, and newspapers (?????? Toa Nyusu; ???? Toa Gaho; ???? Jiji Hodo; ???? Jiji Gaho; ?? Jisei; ?? Kokusai = The International; ?????? Mariyana Jiho; ???? Hawai Shuho; ??????? Rakkasan Nyusu; ???? Jiyu Gaho; and ???? Jin Yao Xin Wen), in Japanese, Chinese, and Burmese. English translation and synopsis are attached to most of the materials. The propaganda materials were issued by Kunming OWI (K-OWI), South East Asian Command- British Psychological Warfare Division (SEAC-BPWD), Political Military Committee of the National Government of China (PMNC), Central Propaganda Section of the Chinese Government (CPSCG), the Association of Japanese Democratic Revolutionary Comrades (AIDRC), Manila Psychological Warfare Branch-U.S. Army (PWB-USA), Kunming OWI Chinese Section (K-OWI-CS), and the Japanese People's Emancipation League (JPEL) in Yenan, China. Also includes a handwritten content list in English compiled by Yoneda. In pocket, one booklet, including information on a Japanese POW, ???? Takada Bokuo, his biographical information and experience with the US military after being captured, in Japanese and Chinese; "??? Imoncho = A Japanese Consolatory Letter" by ??? Hanzawa Akira, including his consolatory cartoons; and the Japanese POW interrogation documents of "Ogata, Koichi" and "Kawashima, Junsei" conducted by Yoneda in 1944.
    - Propaganda Materials (3 of 6), 1945 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      One scrapbook titled: USOWI APO 627. Contains propaganda materials, such as ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets] and a newspaper, ???? Zi You Hua Bao, in English and Chinese, issued by Kunming OWI (K-OWI). English translation and synopsis are attached to each material.
    - Propaganda Materials (4 of 6), circa 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets] propaganda materials, including some issues of a newspaper, ???? Ryukyu Shuho, and leaflets in Japanese. English translation and synopsis are attached to each material.
    - Propaganda Materials (5 of 6), 1943, 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Includes a military song book: ??????? Saishin Ryuko Gunkashu. Ed. by ???????? Dai Nihon Seinen Rengokai. [United States]: Showa Shobo, 1943?; a list of propaganda materials; and manuscripts of the propaganda materials, including "Kiri leaflets" with English annotation. In Japanese, English, and Chinese.
    - Propaganda Materials and Booklets (6 of 6), 1944 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Items are stored in Box 48 (oversize).
    - Documents Including Reports, Photographs, Propaganda Leaflets, Correspondence, News Clippings, and Postcards, 1940-1991, bulk 1944-1946 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Documents including interrogation reports with photographs of Japanese POWs (Koichi Ogata and Junsei Kawashima) conducted by Yoneda in 1945; a report of interrogations conducted at Myitkyina, from July 28 to August 4, 1944, including thirty one Japanese prisoners; Yoneda's membership and certificate cards for Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States and the OWI Psychological Warfare Team; ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets] propaganda leaflets with English translation and synopsis; a book list on anti-Japanese soldiers published in China; correspondence; and news clippings. Also includes Yoneda's writings, including "Propaganda Work in CBI" and a review article, and two postcards with drawings by Keiko Akiba (= Keiko Fukuda).
    - Photographs and Portraits, 1944-1955 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      Black and white photographs and a negative depicting the USOWI activities in Burma, India, and China during the battles. Includes the USOWI staff group photographs. Also includes three pieces of Yoneda's portraits drawn by G. Corley, an OWI artist. Most of the items are annotated in English.
    - Ex-CBI Roundup: China, Burma, India. Laurens, Iowa: Ex-CBI Roundup, 1978 December-1995 July (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Four issues and some extracts from a magazine, "Ex-CBI Roundup: China, Burma, India", which was published by and for former members of U.S. units stationed in China-Burma-India theater during World War II.
    - Veterans Affairs Documents, 1945-1980, bulk 1945-1950 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Yoneda's application forms, letters, and certificate card for Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States, to request patient care, federal benefits to himself and his dependents, including home purchase, business use purchase, and educational assistance.
    - Propaganda Materials and Booklets (6 of 6), 1944 (Box 48, Folder 4)